Finding Aid for Burlingame Congregational United Church of Christ records, 1924-2009
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Burlingame Congregational United Church of Christ records 1924-2009
Burlingame Congregational United Church of Christ (Wyoming, Mich.)
2009157 Ba 2
Congregational church established in Wyoming Township, a suburb of Grand Rapids, in 1924. The church, subsequently renamed Burlingame Congregational United Church of Christ, disbanded in 2009. Church records document the history and activities of the church, and include registers of baptisms, marriages, and burials; also publications, scrapbooks, and records of women’s clubs.
12 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records came from the church (Donor no. 10230 ) in July 2009.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Burlingame Congregational Church was chartered April 28, 1924. Growing out of Grand Rapids Park Congregational Church, the church reflected the growth of Wyoming Township and the need for another Congregational Church. On December 4, 1925, a new building was dedicated.
By the end of 1927 there were 178 in Sunday School and 110 church members. The Rev. Arden Johnson was the pastor from 1925 to 1929. For the following two years, the Rev. Francis Burchell, who was also a dentist, served as interim pastor. He was succeeded by the Rev. Alfred Allard who served 1931 to 1936. The depression brought the church financial problems and loss of membership. Many of the state church officers wanted to close the church, but the Rev. Edwin Richard Evans was assigned to see if the church could be saved. He immediately set about rebuilding the church. Over the next seventeen years the church prospered. The membership grew, the building was enlarged, and an organ was purchased. At the age of sixty-six, Rev. Evans decided to seek a smaller church in a small town.
When Rev. Homer E. Dalrymple came in 1954, the church was crowded and in the need of a new larger building. A canvass committee was appointed to raise funds. Within three years, this committee reached its goal and a building committee was organized. Ground breaking was March 2, 1958, and dedication January 11, 1959. The Rev. Dalrymple resigned effective June 30, 1971, after a pastorate of seventeen years.
The Rev. William Herold was installed August 15, 1971, and served until 1976. He was followed by Leland Booker (1977-1981) the Rev. David Lee Smith (1981-2005), and the Rev. George Miller (2005-2009). Beginning in the 1970s and 1980s, the church experienced dwindling attendance and an increasingly aging membership. When combined with the high cost of maintaining the church facility, the inevitable decision was made in July 2009 to disband.
The records of Burlingame Congregational United Church of Christ have been arranged into the following series: Church registers; Annual Reports; Church Newsletter; Church Bulletins; Scrapbooks; Miscellaneous; Women's Organizations; and Men's Organizations. Members of the church were careful in maintaining the history of Burlingame. The scrapbooks, in particular, contain a complete record of activities from 1924 to 1981. Included in these volumes are photographs, clippings, and programs from church activities, as well as historical notes about the church and biographical material on church pastors and various members. Also of value are the church registers which are both the minutes of the annual church meetings and the record of church functions and membership, notably baptisms, marriages, and burials.
Subjects:
Burlingame Congregational United Church of Christ (Wyoming, Mich.); Congregational churches--Michigan--Wyoming.; Registers of births, etc.--Michigan--Wyoming.; United Church of Christ--Michigan--Wyoming.; Women--Religious life--Michigan.; Wyoming (Mich.)--Church history.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Church registers
  - Minutes of annual meetings, lists of members received and removed, record of baptisms, marriages, and burials
    - 1924-1941 (Box 1)
      (also includes minutes of special meetings, 1926-1954)
    - 1942-1967 (Box 1)
    - 1956-2008 (Box 1)
      (the volume does not include minutes of annual meetings)
- Annual Reports, in loose-leaf binders
  - 1924-1963 (Box 1)
    (early portion of the binder consists of photocopies of the 1924-1941 church register)
  - 1964-1985 (Box 1)
  - 1986-2009 (Box 2)
- Church Newsletter: Burlingame Buzzings, in loose-leaf binders
  - 1955-1964 (Box 2)
  - 1965-1971 (Box 2)
  - 1972-1976 (Box 2)
  - 1977-1980 (Box 3)
  - 1981-1984 (Box 3)
  - 1985-1987 (Box 3)
  - 1988-1989 (Box 4)
  - 1990-1991 (Box 4)
  - 1992-1993 (Box 4)
  - 1994-1995 (Box 5)
  - 1996-1999 (Box 5)
  - 2000-2003 (Box 5)
  - 2004-2009 (Box 5)
- Church Bulletins, in loose-leaf binders beginning in 1955
  - 1926-1927 (Box 6)
  - 1928 (Box 6)
  - 1955-1958 (Box 6)
  - 1959-1975 (Box 6)
    (scattered bulletins for 1964-1975)
  - 1976-1982 (Box 6)
  - 1984-1987 (Box 7)
  - 1988-1990 (Box 7)
  - 1991-1993 (Box 7)
  - 1994-1996 (Box 8)
  - 1997-1998 (Box 8)
  - 1999-2002 (Box 8)
  - 2003-2007 (Box 9)
  - 2008-July 26, 2009 (Box 9)
- Scrapbooks
  (include photographs, clippings, programs, historical and biographical notes)
  - 1924-1981 (Box 9)
  - 1981-2009 (Box 10)
    (include photographic slides accumulated for the 70th anniversary celebration in 1994)
- Miscellaneous
  - Church minute book 1945-1951 (Box 10)
  - Pastoral search committee records 2004-2005 (Box 10)
  - Deceased members biographies 1980s-1990s (Box 10)
    (arranged alphabetically and containing copies of newspaper obituaries and notes about the individual's family)
- Women's Organizations
  - Hamilton Circle
    - Minute book 1925-1926 (Box 11)
    - Minute book 1929-1936 (Box 11)
    - Minute book 1936-1947 (Box 11)
    - Minute book 1948-1954 (Box 11)
    - Minute book 1954-1958 (Box 11)
    - Financial record book 1955-1965 (Box 11)
  - Chapel Circle
    - Minute book 1957-February 1963 (Box 11)
    - Minute book March 1963-September 1971 (Box 11)
    - Minute book October 1971-1986 (Box 11)
    - Minute book 1986-2002 (Box 11)
    - Minute book 1979-1986 (rough draft) (Box 11)
  - Women's Fellowship
    - Minute book 1959-1965 (Box 11)
    - Minute book 1973-1983 (Box 11)
    - Minute book 1983-1996 (Box 11)
  - Women's group (unidentified, probably Burlingame Circle)
    - Minute book 1938 (Box 12)
  - Avery Group
    - Record book 1941-1968 (Box 12)
  - Priscilla Circle
    - Minute book 1946-1962 (Box 12)
    - Minute book 1963-1989 (Box 12)
- Men's Group
  - Men of Burlingame (Men's Fellowship) minutes 1951-1959 (Box 12)
  - Notebook containing copies of clippings and other materials relating to activities of the men's group at the church (Box 12)